[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine online at computer.org software
welcome to software engineering radio
i'm your host brijesh ahmad and today my
guest is swizzex teller
swiss is a senior software engineer
instructor blogger vlogger conference
speaker and author his career in high
growth san francisco startups changed
how he thinks about code and he's
sharing those lessons in his senior
mindset newsletter he is currently
working with tia as a senior software
engineer
he has published several books and video
courses including react for dataviz.com
serverlessreact.dev data visualization
53.js
serverlesshandbook.dev and why
programmers work at night
he has trained the engineering teams for
multiple fortune 500 companies on react
redux graphql serverless and other
modern web technologies swiss welcome to
software engineering radio is there
anything i missed in your bio that you'd
like to add
hey thanks for having me it's a
surprisingly comprehensive bio i think
you got literally everything i've ever
done
excellent in the episode today we will
cover various aspects about being a
senior software engineer we will start
by covering the basics and then move to
cover influencing leadership mentorship
learning performance management and
career path so let's start with the
basics
how do you define a true senior software
engineer years of tenure job title
knowledge what matters
honestly i think the
years of tenure are probably
the least correlated with you being a
true senior software engineer
you see this a lot especially in quickly
growing companies where people
just for sticking around get a senior
title because you know you've been with
the company for a couple of years they
have to do something
to and so what we get is this title
inflation where i've now heard stories
of even people getting the senior
engineer title but from being hired
straight out of college just because
they have college experience it's
getting kind of weird really but
i think that's great i think if you do
get the title i would definitely take it
because it does help your career to like
titles help your careers and that's why
we give titles out and it's always nice
to get a title
but i would say that once you have that
title or if you want to get that title
based on merit rather than just years on
the job
i would focus primarily on how you
approach solving problems
and i think the challenge that a lot of
people run into is as engineers we like
to get really focused on the engineering
aspects and the coding aspects and we
kind of forget about
why it is that we do engineering and why
it is that we write code and i think
that the more senior you get the more
you become focused on
using code as a tool to solve problems
and to achieve business results rather
than code for its own sake so i i would
say that that's the main difference
between someone who's a mid-level or
junior is that they get they're more
focused on the code and how to actually
do the thing rather than later when
you're more senior you become more
focused on the problem solving and the
business stuff and writing the actual
code is almost like i wouldn't say
exactly an afterthought but it's just
the final delivery of
the actual engineering process that
happened before right and is that what
you mean by the senior engineer mindset
you know are those the identifiable
behaviors of a senior engineer yeah
exactly i would say that the main
identified behaviors of a senior
engineer are
this relentless focus on
solving problems rather than writing the
code and
something that you often see in this
transition is people starting to say
that
they don't care about the code or that
the code itself doesn't really matter
obviously it still matters to an extent
you don't want to write code that's
going to be impossible to maintain but
again there's a trick there because
you're not focused on the code itself
being perfect and the craft of writing
really amazing code you're focused on
the business problem or the business
metric of maintainability because you're
going to have to evolve the code over
time i think the main difference really
is that
the senior mindset at least to me means
that focus on
using code to solve problems rather than
thinking about the code itself as like a
craft
it's still a craft but it's the purpose
is not the craft that's what hobbies are
for and that's what site projects are
for
when you're coding in a business context
the business is the the actual thing
you're thinking about
okay so you're focusing on solving the
business problem rather than
you know building the best solution
which might not be the best fit for
solving the business problem yeah
exactly that's a really good way of
putting it because you see this a lot in
startups i've been playing around with
advising some
startups in the very early stages
or you can see it outside projects as
well what often happens is that
engineers get so focused on oh yes this
is a nice greenfield project we're going
to make everything perfect we're going
to design the perfect framework we're
going to find the perfect library and
we're going to spend
multiple weeks or months making sure
that this is really amazing
and they completely forget that
even if you build the best code
and there's no users for it you've just
wasted a bunch of time what you really
should do is
make a solution that's fit for the
current stages you're at get it out
quickly get feedback from the market and
then improve it because
whether you spend a week building
something or you spend two months
building something i can almost promise
you that the first solution that you
build is going to be wrong regardless of
how long it took regardless of how much
thought went into it regardless of
how many blogs you read or how many
books and how perfectly you designed it
the first solution is always going to be
wrong so it's much better to get it out
quickly and figure out the right
solution first and then when you know
the right solution then you can think
about how to polish it up and how to
make it better how to make it easier to
maintain more
architecturally correct etc
because the other thing that comes with
that is also
at least for me i don't know about the
listeners of this podcast but for most
of us you know we are not google we are
not dealing with the kind of scale where
you have
billions of users using your software
every day
so you can get away with
not being as tightly engineered as
google you know it's same as
when rocket scientists are building a
rocket ship at spacex that's going to
cost
i don't know 100 million dollars when it
blows up and doesn't deliver payload to
orbit that's a very different
engineering criteria than when you're
building
let's say that colin furzi guy who
builds really cool things on youtube and
he built a rocket-powered go-kart or
rocket-powered sled that he used in his
backyard
very different engineering criteria and
i can promise you that if colin furzi
was building with the exact same
engineering practices as nasa or spacex
that video would never come out because
he would still be working on it 10 years
later
in one of your blog posts you have said
a senior engineer works as a force
multiplier
can you expand on this
yeah so the force multiplier concept i
think originally comes from the
military or the navy but the idea is
that
force multipliers are the kind of people
that you put on a team
and they make everyone around them work
better perform at a higher level they
make the whole team just better at
delivering projects at delivering work
so what often happens with senior
engineer is that
the kind of problems you're solving
start outgrowing the amount of work you
can do yourself this is even an example
that
forget who the author is but the
mythical man month where
it's a whole book about working together
as a team and about how
the most famous quote from that book
that everyone remembers is
adding engineers to a late project make
project makes the project even later so
what they take out of it is oh
if adding more engineers makes projects
slower then i'm just going to be the
superhero who gets everything done and
it's amazing
and like i'm going to have low
communication overhead i'm going to be
able to think of everything on my own
and i'm just going to deliver this
amazing code and it's going to be great
and that's true
it is much easier in a lot of cases to
work on your own but the other part of
that book that a lot of people ignore is
that he says
yes a single super talented engineer can
work faster because they don't have
communication overhead
but
there is a limit to how much you can
actually just even just typing on a
keyboard takes time so a single engineer
is never going to be able to deliver a
software project like an operating
system or a modern web app that runs
like a 100 million dollar business it's
just
i mean you could it's just going to take
you 10 years and if it takes you 10
years the market is going to change by
then and nobody's going to care so come
back to the force multiplier part the
way you can take that into your own
career is to embrace the idea that
modern software development is a team
sport and you can be the person who
makes everyone on your team faster
because
a team that has
one 10x engineer and five 1x engineers
kind of milling around not doing
anything
is going to be much slower than a team
that has a one 5x engineer and that 5x
engineer decides to
spend most of their time getting all of
the other engineers to be i don't know
2x or 3x because
if i got my math right
5 plus 15 is more than 10 plus 4.
right
we will touch more about you know
building that high performing team but
right now we're going to transition into
learning and we'll touch on some aspects
on the importance of continuous learning
as a senior engineer you get pulled in
multiple directions multiple projects
how do you find the time to learn how do
you keep motivating yourself pushing
yourself to learn something new
i love that question because
most of the engineers i've met i would
almost rather tell them to stop learning
so many new things and try to focus on a
few things a little bit more because one
thing that happens is that especially
when you're reading a lot of a lot of
stuff online
is really aimed at beginners and juniors
so what happens with many senior
engineers that i know is that they are
juniors in 50 different technologies
instead of
knowing about 50 technologies and being
able to pick them up if they get there
and then being really deep in one or two
and this is kind of tricky because going
really deep in one technology or maybe
even five technologies if that's what
you like
is
a better bang for your buck than
learning the surface of everything but
knowing the surface of everything is
kind of useful because it helps you jump
around so
you ask me more about the motivation and
finding the time
i don't think
it's really something you should make
time for because
you know we're not really at school
anymore
if you need to make time to learn
something
it might not actually be worth learning
i personally much rather go where my
interests take me if i find something
interesting i dive in and i explore and
i try to figure it out if i run into a
problem at work that's a really good
time to be like hey i found this problem
and i have a problem that i want to
solve
which is really good motivation to learn
how to solve that problem especially if
you're a senior engineer you can very
often find yourself in a situation where
you are pretty much the world's leading
expert in that specific issue in your
specific company in your specific
situation
there will be times where you look
around you and there's nobody on your
team you can ask for help there's nobody
on the internet who has ever solved
anything like that you can find people
who've solved something kind of similar
or you can find other experts to talk
with who have who are just really good
at thinking through things
but you're kind of just going to have to
push the edge of human knowledge a
little further in that regard and i find
that to be a really good way to learn it
for me as well because it's like
solving the problem is the motivation
part
figuring out the solution is the
learning part because you're learning
how to do something new and with some
luck you've also learned something that
nobody else in the world has figured out
before or at least not in your
particular situation and then if you
write about it you can make it easier
for others as well and the writing about
it i find is really useful to help you
clarify your thoughts and really cement
the knowledge like explaining it to an
audience really helps you
clarify to yourself and it's a good hack
to find blind spots in your reasoning
like one thing i like to say is that
every senior engineer when they make a
decision
should really be able to explain why
they made that decision
and if you don't know why you made a
decision there's a very high likelihood
that
there's some part of your process that
you don't fully understand yet that
would be good to dig into and learn more
about
yeah does that answer your question it
does yeah i think if you are motivated
enough and passionate enough about
something you know you do find the time
that's what you're trying to say
basically you find the time and
making the time for that at work
is actually part of the job i think a
lot of engineers are afraid of learning
on the job
but the job isn't
banging out perfect code the job is
solving problems so if they give you a
problem you don't know how to solve
learning how to solve it is actually
part of the job and
so completely something you should be
doing
on company time and i think that also
makes a lot more time than people have
on
nights and weekends around the job
okay how important is coaching and
teaching for a senior engineer
i think it's a big part of the job
actually if you're
like that's part of the force multiplier
thing we mentioned earlier is that
when you're on a team and you consider
it part of your role to make everyone on
the team
better faster just
more efficient at solving problems
giving them that mentoring and
perspective is a big part of it so i
think
everyone who's a senior engineer should
at least think about mentoring others
and coaching them
and the other aspect is that
it frees you up to more interesting
parts of the job like one thing i try to
always focus on when i join a company or
whenever i accept a project is
i'm trying to
work myself out of that role or work
myself out of that job
because
if you're the only person in the company
who can solve a specific set of problems
then you will always be the person who
is solving those problems and
you can't take vacations you can leave
the team you can't go on to solving more
interesting problems
and if you train others to solve those
problems or if you just help them along
if you encourage them hey
you go do this i already know how to do
it i've done i've built a login form 50
times in my life
why don't you build this login form and
ask me questions and i'll help you out
and that way the next time that you have
to build a login form there's not two
people on the team who can do it and you
can keep working on something that you
find more interesting rather than
something that you've been doing forever
teaching is a completely different skill
set compared to cutting code while some
are naturally good at instruction not
everybody is
how do you improve your teaching skills
i think with teaching skills it's one of
those things that you
just have to do if you jump in and start
teaching and the more you do it the
easier it gets
and you know it's totally fine to run
experiments not every time you try to
explain something it's going to stick
not every time is going to
really
resonate with the person and different
approaches resonate with different
people so what i what i personally try
to do
is kind of try different things with
different people i
i often if you go through my blogging
catalog you'll see that
i have a lot of articles that are
roughly on the same idea because i'm
developing the idea over time and i'm
also figuring out how to explain the
idea how to talk about it in a way that
resonates with people you can do the
same when you're mentoring at work you
can try just throwing somebody in the
deep end and see if they ask you
questions if they're not the kind of
person who has questions you can instead
try to next time they pick a task that
you don't think they'll be able to do
you ask them hey let's meet together
let's figure it out and then
we'll collaboratively come up with a
solution and then you go off and you
code it or
you can use pr's and like pull requests
and code review are also a really good
approach for teaching where
somebody makes a draft of a solution
they they solve it to the best of their
ability and you can then go in and give
them uh pointers and be like hey this
could be done differently and explain
your reasoning why it should be done
differently because like the core of my
teaching philosophy is to always try to
explain my reasoning behind why i'm
giving a suggestion
because that way
over time people get more exposed to my
reasoning they can start reason in
similar ways on their own and next time
they won't have to ask or they will just
do it
a better way the first time because they
know the reasoning or
this also happens sometimes they can
just be like hey swiss this reasoning
makes no sense i'm not gonna make the
change you propose and that's fine
because it means that i was most likely
wrong if i can't explain why i think
something should be done a different way
or if my reasoning doesn't actually
match reality like i had an assumption
that isn't actually true
that's totally fine that's what
collaboration is all about but yeah i
think fundamentally getting better at
teaching is mostly about trying and
seeing what sticks and it's also a very
humbling experience because you very
often learn that you don't actually know
what you were talking about and that
gives you those pointers for what we
were saying earlier for jumping into and
learning more things like hey i just
said this should be done differently
i'm not actually able to explain it
which means maybe i don't understand it
as well as i thought i did so i'm going
to go read an article about it read a
book about it and i'm going to learn
more because of that
interesting it's just iterative
development is something which is quite
well established in software development
it's interesting to hear about iterative
teaching as well
so yeah that's something which i'm sure
our listeners will
learn from over the course of your
career you get to know about many best
practices and make many of these part of
your development regime
it's just the way you develop or build
software have you seen any instances
where these best practices have been
codified what challenges are faced in
ensuring the entire team adopts these
best practices
oh that's a really good question so
i think there's
kind of different levels of codifying
best practices
so i think the first level of codifying
a best practice is figuring out what is
the best practice this goes back to what
people say
don't make an abstraction until you've
done something two or three times
because those two or three times
actually inform what the best practice
is going to be you have to see how
something works for a pattern to emerge
then when a pattern emerges what you can
do is codify that pattern
by either showing it to the rest of the
team and being and saying hey you know
here's something that has really worked
for me it has worked in these multiple
instances maybe you should try to and
then if people try it and they like it
it's going to become it kind of spreads
almost like a cultural idea within the
team
the good practices
tend to
spread on the team fairly organically
everyone adopts them because they're
also helping them if it's just a good
practice that you read about somewhere
and it doesn't resonate with your team
it might be because
it might be because it's not actually
working for your team
or your team is not at the point yet or
the company isn't at the point yet where
that best practice makes sense like for
example
a lot of the things that google does
don't make sense for my team who's like
30 engineers because we don't need the
overhead process that
thousands of engineers at google use
because we're just not big enough and we
would spend more time following the best
practices than we actually get result
out of
so
don't be afraid of
ideal best practices getting rejected by
your team because they might just not
fit then the next level of these best
practices being codified
is
after the cultural level they can start
turning into like little frameworks or
libraries it's a good way to codify a
best practice is being like hey you know
i'm noticing that everyone on the team
keeps solving the same problem and keeps
solving it in roughly the same way
there's small differences which make it
really annoying to debug in different
places because it looks like the same
thing but it's not actually the same
thing so what you can do is make a
framework out of it or make a small
library for your team to use this is
also where a lot of public open source
libraries come out of it somebody
noticed a pattern saw that it's really
useful in many situations and try to
codify it in code so that others on the
team don't have to keep solving the same
problem
this is like an example from the
front-end space is
why we have so many
form state management libraries is
because it's really hard to get the
right layer of abstraction for a form
state but at the same time
nobody wants to
build state management for a form the
bazillionth time because it's always
pretty much the same and it's really
annoying it's easy to get wrong in
subtle ways so it's much better if you
pick up a library or like a lot of
people they make a library another good
example of this is
on the front end when you're building ui
components
you notice that designers reuse a lot of
these components in different places and
they have basically zero differences
between them because they're following a
design system
if you codify that design system in a ui
library that's specific for your company
and specific for your design system you
then
free your engineers from thinking about
those details every time so instead of
thinking about pixel perfect positioning
of every
element on the page they can just reuse
existing components and focus on the
business logic and like the user flows
instead of the little details and that
speeds up the entire team which again
goes back to our force multiplier stuff
we talked about earlier you notice a
pattern you codify the pattern in some
sort of framework or
a set of functions and then
show it to others and if it's working
for them if it's actually solving their
problems they're going to start using it
and be able to move faster and then as
it spreads through the company you'll
quickly notice that the entire company
is following the same patterns and has
those codified best practices
quite a interesting thought over there
the one which struck me was that a best
practice itself is contextual what might
be a best practice in one organization
might not work as a best practice in
another with a different context
we will now move on from learning and
touch on another important skill a
senior engineer needs to have leadership
any thoughts on how to lead a project
even if you are not managing the people
working on the project
yes so i think this is probably my
favorite part of engineering is the
leadership part like
it's something that a lot of companies
don't really understand some companies
understand it more than others
but you see a lot of this equating of
leadership and management
but
i think that at least in a lot of modern
companies that has split it's been a
trend in silicon valley for the last 10
to maybe 10 20 years and it's kind of
spreading to the rest of the tech
industry in general where
you can be a
engineering leader
and you can lead projects but you're not
actually the direct manager of any of
the team
and i think
that at least for me because i'm very
technically minded that's more
interesting i never want to be
never is a strong word maybe i'll change
my mind at some point but i've never
wanted to be a
like a manager manager somebody who has
to do people management but i do like to
lead projects and i like to have
influence on the team around me and have
like
technical leadership versus people
leadership and
what i mean by that is that
the main difference really is
on whether you are in charge of the
technical direction of a project or
whether you're in charge of the whole
career development and coaching and
people problems people managers are more
focused on their people's careers and
removing obstacles and like
some communication across teams and also
like doing the one-on-ones and that sort
of thing whereas technical leadership is
more about okay
we got a project
that is
way bigger than a single person can
achieve
it might even be bigger than we can
achieve in a single sprint something
that we're going to be working on over
an entire quarter and there's going to
be three teams working on it a couple of
different pms
we're going to be dealing with external
vendors and
you need somebody
who
is kind of at the center of all this or
adjacent to the center who can keep a
coherent technical vision for the
project because what happens a lot is if
there's no responsible person for the
technical direction of a project
you end up with a kind of
mishmash of approaches that
evolve very organically and there's no
i'm trying to come up with an example
but but it's hard to think of something
that's going to make sense to everyone
who's listening but if you've ever
experienced a project that doesn't have
direction a good symptom of that might
be whack-a-mole bugs where
every time you fix a bug five other bugs
show up or when
you're working on
some part of the project and then you
realize
somebody on the other team or even on
your own team is working is solving the
exact same problem just in a different
way in a different place and because you
didn't have that oversight together you
didn't realize that you're working on
the same thing
or another thing that happens is you get
too many cooks in the kitchen where
everyone is trying to solve the problem
in its own way and the architecture
evolves in
strange directions that don't fit
together or
yeah so basically it's kind of hard to
put into words but when you're in a
project like that
it's kind of obvious that it's a mess
and that nobody has a long-term vision
for what they're doing you're just
focused on your current immediate task
and
it's hard to feel a coherent vision so
that's where a technical leader or a
senior engineer can come in and kind of
be like okay we need to solve this
problem
our long-term vision goes in this
direction this is like what we're
building towards for an entire quarter
and you can explain that to everyone
kind of keep them in the same direction
and then
help them slice it up for their
immediate task the way you can often do
that leadership
is back to what i was talking about
earlier where
you're giving them feed you take a code
review for example
and you're giving them feedback and you
kind of nudge them and push them in the
direction of the overall vision so you
say hey
we should do this part that you coded is
great it solves the immediate thing that
you were working on
but i think we should do it this other
way because
next sprint we're solving this other
thing that's similar to this or
because in a quarter we're going in this
direction
where we need to anticipate future needs
not to the extent of completely subduing
everything to our future needs because
that usually doesn't work but more like
you know let's just move slowly in that
direction so
it's kind of i think the way i would
summarize that is that
you can do a lot of technical leadership
by just nudging people in the right
direction so
set a vision in your mind hopefully
align that vision with everyone else on
the team because it's much easier to
nudge them in a direction if they agree
with you
and then kind of nudge and kind of it's
kind of like cat hurting it to an extent
but kind of just with nudging and
gardening and you're like you know let's
go in that direction let's do a little
snip here
i think the gardening analogy probably
works best it's like
when a gardener is trying to make a
bonsai tree or
uh or like a nice beautiful tree in
in a park
the tree grows wherever it wants to grow
what the gardener is doing is cutting
and tying and kind of snipping and
nudging and
and coaxing the tree in the direction
and shape that they want it's very
similar with technical leadership people
are doing organically they're making
changes and you can kind of push them
and nudge them in a direction that
makes a coherent sense across everything
right so if i understood that right
the technical leader provides that
overarching
oversight and leadership and aligns the
architecture to the business vision
and gets the technical team closer and
makes them understand how their tasks
align to that vision
yeah exactly and then
if we want to go more tactical with that
the approach that has worked best for me
is doing uh swarm design sessions at the
beginning of every
story so any story that's a little
bigger than just banging it out in an
hour or two
you kind of get together on a swarm you
get everyone helping design the solution
and
because everyone is designing the
solution together you get a more
coherent solution because everyone was
in the room when it was being designed
everyone understands the solution that
they're building because they helped
come up with it they feel more aligned
because again they've given their input
they've explained what they want they've
explained their concerns
and you as the leader also get to hear
everyone's concerns and then you can
kind of
nudge them towards the desired solution
by asking the right questions
or by proposing the right solution so
like
somebody
suggests a solution that's gonna work
but doesn't take into account something
that
you're keeping in your head as the
overall vision you can say hey how about
this other thing or have you thought
about this task or feature that we're
gonna have to solve next week and then
you can kind of
nudge and shape things in a direction
an important leadership skill is
influencing and you touched on this in
the answer to the question of leading a
project though you might not be line
managing the team members i want to dig
a bit deeper into influencing because i
believe this is a very important skill
set for senior engineers how do you go
about influencing other team members or
teams to use your solution instead of
writing their own
i think influence is
it can be really difficult actually to
have influence because
people are
you know people are their own people i
think many engineers don't actually like
to feel influenced
so
it's a lot like trying to find a good
way to phrase this that doesn't sound
bad but a lot of really experienced
leaders that i've talked to have said
yeah you know managing engineers or
leading engineers is a lot like dealing
with kids
they all think they know best and
they're all very temperamental and they
just want to do what they want to do but
you have to kind of nudge them in the
right direction so like a funny example
from uh that i've heard that works with
raising kids instead of asking them hey
do you want to put your coat on so we
can go outside you say hey do you want
to put on the black coat or the red coat
when we go outside and the kids like oh
yes i love the red coat and they don't
even realize that not wearing a coat is
also an option because that wasn't an
option that was presented to them that's
a little of a kind of a manipulative
trick but it really does work i've seen
this it works on me i've seen it work on
everyone that i've ever tried it on it's
you present a choice and people can make
their own choice but it's among the
options that work for you like a really
good example of where this works is
organizing meetings when you instead of
saying hey
when do you want to meet or hey do you
want to meet about this you can say hey
do you want to talk about this at 3 pm
or at 4 pm
and people are like oh yeah let's talk
about it at 4 pm don't even realize that
you're kind of shoving them towards a
specific
answer and you can do a lot of that when
you're helping design solutions but i
think
the main part of influence really is
ensuring that people feel empowered and
making sure that
it is their decision to do what you
would like them to do you're not going
to win every time and that's like you
know just even thinking about it as
winning is bad
but usually what works with influencing
engineers is
making sure that everyone feels like
their inputs have been heard making sure
that their concerns have been heard
making time for everyone to raise their
concerns with a solution making time for
everyone to propose their solutions and
kind of guiding them towards
making the decision that you think is
the right decision
part of that is also that it could be
that you were wrong and what you think
is the right solution is the wrong
solution so by giving everyone that
opportunity to raise concerns they might
also change your mind and you come up
with a better result a better solution
in the end
the example of meeting reminds me about
a question i meant to ask you in the
time boxing technique you recommend
scheduling meetings back to back and say
that there is nothing worse than a
15-minute break between two meetings
i see two issues here first health how
do you ensure you do not end up sitting
for too long secondly don't you need the
breathing space between meetings to
reflect on what was discussed take notes
etc
so i think this is from my
why programmers work at night book the
idea of time boxing is to
create a time for a certain task so like
this comes from i think it's like
behavior change science that talks about
if you really want to get something done
you shouldn't just say i'm gonna get
this done you have to say i'm gonna get
it done at this time on this day and i'm
going to get started by doing x
so
what time boxing helps with is making
sure that when you get into flow or when
you really fall into it you also have a
stopping point because
you can't think straight for a very long
time
so there's a couple of things that go
into time boxing the
one side of the issue is that you're
giving yourself a time limit because
that gives you a little bit of oomph
because you have a deadline you say i
want to finish this in an hour
it also gives you a stopping point
because it's very easy to get
stuck in a problem and like you know
you're working on a bug and you're just
banging your head against the wall and
because there's nothing stopping you you
keep banging your head against the wall
whereas it turns out that if you step
away go for a walk for 10 minutes come
back suddenly it's much easier to solve
the other thing is context switching is
very expensive mentally
so
working on a million things at the same
time or switching every 10 minutes can
be very taxing on focus and on actually
making progress on anything
and that's where time boxing comes in if
you put similar tasks together you can
kind of get them out of the way and then
you have more time later in the day or
before those tasks to focus and do deep
work there's a lot of literature about
this out there there's a deep work by
cal newport atomic habits by
james clear are both really good books
if you want to go to more underlying
sources bj fogg talks about this a lot
he has a whole course at stanford and he
does academic research in this area but
anyway the thing with meetings and with
taking notes between meetings is that
as a senior engineer the more that you
have a team around you it's almost like
you become a decision machine
you're
less and less expected to do the deep
work yourself
rather than unblocking others and making
decisions so you can see this a lot in
how ceos behave or how business leaders
behave
it's very similar for senior engineers
especially the bigger the team around
you where
coming together with the team
talking for 10 minutes or 15 minutes
getting everyone's input and then be
taking a bet and making a decision based
on your experience based on where the
team is at based on what you think and
being like okay so i've heard everyone's
input let's go with option a
and that's it that's all that everyone
anyone needed from you it was that
decision because either they weren't
sure enough of themselves to make it or
they need somebody like you who has a
bigger stance at the company somebody to
take the heat when the decision goes
wrong and decisions often go wrong and
it's important to be the kind of person
who can say okay i think
option a has a 60 of chance of working
option b has a 40 chance of working
let's go with option a and if i'm wrong
i'm going to be the one who stands in
front of our boss or the product owner
or whoever and explains we made a
decision this is why it was the right
decision at the time it didn't work out
here's how we're going to fix it and in
terms of taking notes or taking breaks
between those meetings a lot of that can
actually be outsourced a good meeting
that's well run
means that you don't have to do a lot of
pre-reading you don't have to do a lot
of pre-work because you can use the
meeting itself to get the relevant
information because again you know what
you need to make a decision so asking
those questions of the people on the
call is a lot more effective than them
trying to predict what you're going to
ask and giving you all the info in
advance so that can work faster and then
for notes you can give that to somebody
else that's again comes back to
the leadership and influence part you
can empower people to take their own
notes to make their own subtasks or to
slice up the ticket and that way you're
free to spend more time on that critical
piece that only you can do which is
making decisions based on your
experience using the neural network in
your head that you've trained over
a long career to
make those decisions much quicker
because you've seen how they play out in
the past
right so by time boxing you were
indicating more of grouping the similar
tasks together
and you know so to reduce the context
switching rather than discouraging you
know taking breaks in between and not
you know
negatively impacting your health yeah
and like one thing i actually do a lot
and i really like this about my current
company because everyone does this
we put lunches and breaks and walking
the dogs and stuff like that on our
calendars so other people know not to
schedule meetings over that
any good tools for time boxing
honestly out of all of the tools i've
tried
the one that ends up working best is
just my calendar so what i've been
trying to do a lot is just
every week or every day kind of look at
what i need to do or what i want to get
done and just put it on the calendar and
say i'm going to be working on this for
half an hour or an hour at this time
it's not perfect because you then have
to also you have to be in the mental
space to do that but i think with some
practice you can get there or you can
shift things around
i would now like to ask a few questions
about mentorship
how important is it to have a mentor
yeah i think mentors are
they're super helpful you can always go
through life without mentors there's
also like
mentors are like a force multiplier on
yourself same with coaching it's like
you can as a smart engineer talented
motivated you can always figure things
out on your own
but it's a lot easier if you can ask
someone and they
say oh yeah you know i've done this 50
million times in my career here's how
you do it or here's how i would think
about it that's super helpful getting
official mentors can be really hard
it's
easy within a company where especially
for junior engineers companies often
assign mentors
for more senior engineers you kind of
have to find someone in the company or
around that resonates with you and then
you know just
take them out for coffee every week or
every other week and kind of talk about
things the main thing about mentorship
is that it's very
mentee driven so nobody is going to sit
around and wait to give you advice it's
more like you have to go out and talk to
them and explain your situation and like
not exactly pull things out of them but
find somebody who's willing to talk to
you and listen to you and
share ideas and just ask them questions
and
see
whatever you're struggling with whatever
you're dealing with just ask them get
help
like the most basic example of
mentorship in tech companies are code
reviews
for more like career mentorship often
your manager does that although in
bigger companies that can get a little
tricky because of misaligned incentives
just making friends in the industry is
super helpful where you can be like
find somebody who's more experienced and
just talk to them you know enjoy their
company have kind of an unofficial
mentorship going on
like there's a lot of people thinking
back on my career that were my mentors
and neither of us probably realized that
they were my mentors at the time it was
just oh yeah i actually ended up getting
a lot of really good advice from this
person and i now consider them my mentor
another approach is kind of like
mastermind groups this is more like peer
mentoring where
you find a group of people who are going
through similar life phase similar
career phase similar technical
challenges as you and just
set up a call with them once a week or
grab a beer once a week and just talk
about what you're doing what you're
going through and kind of mentor each
other in real time that's also really
good practice for
mentoring others in a more formal
position
as a senior engineer it's your
responsibility to ensure that you have a
high performing team so i wanted to ask
some questions about performance
management
what factors should one consider while
managing the performance of senior
engineers
i think the best analogy for managing
the performance of senior engineers
comes from like the shipping industry
where there was a famous example online
where i think it was ups or something
like that
was paying workers per hour
and by workers i mean here delivery
drivers who like who are in a van with a
bunch of packages in the trunk and they
have to deliver them if you pay them by
the hour it turns out all of the
deliveries were late all the time
everything was always late because
people were incentivized to work as slow
as possible you know if i work 10 hours
i'm gonna get paid more than if i get it
done in six hours but then the company
switched to paying per
i think per package delivered or per van
emptied something like that and as soon
as they started paying per package
delivered delivery rates doubled i think
the amount of time drivers spent was
like half or even less than that because
it's like okay well i'm getting paid
let's say a hundred dollars
to deliver 50 packages
i can either get that done in three
hours or in six hours obviously they're
going to want to do it in three hours so
it's very similar with engineers where
if we are valued for
delivering features or delivering
business value we're going to naturally
approach our work much differently than
if we're incentivized for but in seats
time and like button seat is probably
the worst possible way to manage the
performance of a team it usually shows
that the manager in question or the
business in question
doesn't really trust their engineers to
be hard-working people doesn't trust
their engineers to
do the work
and that's why like a lot of bad
managers manage by making sure if you're
available from ten to six or nine to
five or whatever then i'm sure you're at
least working i might not know if the
work is getting done i might not care
but at least i know you're there and
you're trying so that's what i care
about and usually those companies are
very slow at shipping they fall behind
with the competition whereas companies
who focus on deliverables where it's
like we don't care how long this takes
we don't care how you do it even to an
extent
we have this
okr objective and key result we have
this business metric that we want to hit
go figure it out have fun
make sure that i don't know sales are up
by 10 by the end of the quarter and or
like just increase sales by 10 and the
faster you do it the better
people approach that situation a lot
differently they
naturally are more incentivized to work
harder to find more of those quick
solutions and kind of hacks like we
talked about earlier where
actually i'm not sure if we talked about
that but they just end up shipping
faster and being more focused on the
actual results rather than pontificating
and
having long debates about what is the
perfect way to write something because
the business usually doesn't really care
about the perfect way to code something
they care about the business result so
if you also incentivize engineers based
on business results and if you manage
them based on business results
everything else tends to kind of fall in
line with that so that's what i've seen
work best and we do this at my current
company and i think
everyone that has joined from product
owners to engineers
like there's this moment after two or
three weeks or maybe a month and they're
like
i have never seen a team move this fast
before like i've never worked at a team
that's able to deliver projects so fast
and so accurately and it's all because
we are managed and we manage ourselves
based on
business deliverables based on achieving
results rather than on doing the work
in summary make out comes the primary
metric for performance management is
that right yeah
yeah based on outcomes instead of inputs
the last section is questions on growth
and career progression
what training should an company ideally
provide to senior engineers are there
any companies that are doing a good job
on this
i think there's a lot of companies out
there that kind of struggle with
figuring out what to do with very senior
engineers
the main thing is that
you know one thing i've noticed in my
career is that once you get that senior
engineer title it's like
a senior engineer could be anyone
between five years of experience and 30
years of experience they're all senior
engineers so it kind of feels like your
career almost like ends at that point
when you become senior but i think
what's hiding underneath there is that
yes a lot of people go into management
but if you ask me that's a different
career you don't actually get promoted
into management you're changing careers
and you can go from management back to
coding and back to being an engineer but
it is a different career it's a
different skill set it's a different
path but if you want to stay engineer
you can keep growing on the engineering
track
which
to be honest often looks like it goes
outside the company because yes there's
principal engineers and i think there's
microsoft or somebody has distinguished
fellows and stuff like that where it's
almost like being a tenured professor
and you can basically do whatever you
want from what i've heard
there's very few of those there's a lot
more managers than there are
distinguished fellows at these companies
it's going to be very hard to get there
what you can do instead and what you can
focus on instead is
finding ways to solve bigger and better
problems so
companies
often don't have
any new challenges to offer senior
engineers because the company itself
isn't really growing isn't getting that
much better so there's nowhere for
senior engineers to go what you can do
in that case rather than what often
happens is you get bogged down into
being an architecture astronaut and so
making perfect solutions you can change
companies to go into a company that does
have those bigger better problems
because you know a senior engineer at a
five-person startup
is a very very different job than a
senior engineer
at a thousand engineer company and also
your growth is very different that like
if your company is growing from
like i'm gonna make up some numbers but
let's use employees as a proxy for
everything else if your company is
growing from 10 employees to
15 employees in two years
that's going to be a much different
experience than if you're growing from
let's say 20 employees to 300 employees
in a year
you're going to learn a lot more at the
company that's growing faster and the
challenges that you're solving and the
things that you get to see are going to
become interesting a lot faster and you
can stay a senior engineer at the
company that's growing like that for a
very very long time because they just
keep having new and more interesting
challenges or you can switch to a bigger
company and get new more interesting
bigger challenges that way that kind of
force you
to think differently and go bigger
what skills would you focus on as a
junior engineer to become a true senior
engineer
so i think
most junior engineers here i mean
through real junior engineers who don't
have a lot of experience in
actually delivering coding and results i
would focus primarily on
getting better technically focus on the
technical skills so that
later when you are a senior or even when
you're a mid-level
you decoding is not holding you back
it's almost like a second thought is
how to deliver the result versus
designing the result then as you become
a maid and a senior
start shifting more towards
focusing on how to solve the problem and
how to design a solution rather than the
actual implementation and then also
start adding those leadership skills and
solving bigger problems and
one thing that everyone can learn and
that everyone can work on is the
ownership mentality
this is something i talk a lot about in
my newsletter as well is
really owning the thing that you've been
tasked with solving it's like hey even
as a junior when you get a subtask or
like a small part of the overall problem
really own that figure out all the ways
you can make it better write all the
tests like be proactive
on the result on the outcome understand
how it adds up to the overall picture
but really like don't
quote something up and throw it over the
fence and it's fine enough it's more
like
code something up really think about how
you can make it better think about how
you can write tests that prove that it's
correct think about how you can test it
yourself then like you know i need to
work on better examples for the
ownership stuff but the idea is that
you take responsibility for the result
of whatever piece of the puzzle you've
been tasked with and really own that
part and kind of project manage yourself
own it focus on delivering the result
rather than just
doing something others told you to do
and then moving on
what advice would you have for junior
engineers is it better to join a big or
a small company
i think that really depends on
what kind of person you are or maybe not
what kind of person you are but what
interests you
if you go into a smaller company
you're going to get a lot more ownership
a lot more responsibility a lot faster
it's almost like being thrown in the
deep end like i started my career
as the only
programmer in the entire company and
that was great
it really forced me to learn a lot
really really quickly but it also meant
that i was doing weird things that don't
make sense to anyone who's ever worked
in a professional environment before
i was building solutions that i probably
didn't need to build because if i had
someone like a mentor or a more
experienced peer they could be like
swiss
that is stupid just use a library i know
you don't know about the library but you
don't have to build everything from
scratch yourself but i did because i
just didn't know about these things
right
whereas at the bigger company
you get a much more
streamlined experience you get to see
how big companies work you get a lot of
support from everyone around you you get
people mentoring you if you run into any
issues you can just go ask somebody some
of your peers you get it's a lot more
like being thrown in the shallow end of
the pool
with
five lifeguards around you who are
helping you and making sure that
you're going to
learn how to swim properly so
i think both can work personally i like
being thrown in the deep end and
figuring things out but it does mean
that later when i get better advice or
when i learn better things i have to
unlearn a lot of bad practices
whereas somebody who starts the big
company learns a lot of good practices
by default but then might also struggle
with growing much slower having a slower
career path and then if they do ever
transition to smaller companies because
they want more of that ownership or they
want more responsibility
it can be hard to adapt uh
large company thinking to a smaller
company where you have to move faster
and be more willing to experiment and do
weird things
so in summary take the job there are
pros and cons to each and make the best
of the opportunity yeah exactly
finally i would like to conclude our
session with a couple of questions that
are quite generic
industry trends what resources do you
use to stay up to date
it's really bad but i've been
using twitter for a really long time
because i feel if you follow the right
people on twitter it's like
yes you see a lot of weird politics and
stupid stuff but you also see a lot of
early ideas and early
trends like there's been a lot of
examples where i saw somebody tweeting
about an experiment or thinking about
doing something and then later three
months later or six months later it
became a really big seminal talk at a
major conference that shifted the entire
field in that direction so that's a
really good way to keep up with future
trends are going to be like but that's a
lot of work and that can be hard and
there's a lot of noise
keeping up with
trends that are already here is easier
through like books
when you start seeing a lot of books
being published about the topic
that's usually a little late into the
trend or later because books usually
take two or three years of research
before somebody publishes so you're a
little more behind but you get to see
things that have survived the test of
time things that are actually going to
be
the trends for the next 10 20 years
rather than for the next six months
newsletters are also great
and i think kind of
what works for me is kind of just
keeping an eye out looking at hacker
news sometimes looking at reddit twitter
seeing what books people are talking
about and then kind of following trends
that way you are writing a book titled
why programmers work at night
do senior programmers also work at night
honestly i think yes and no
the main trust of that book was that
people work at night
but the night time can actually be early
in the morning and it's more about
finding focus to work on your own things
i think
a lot has changed in the industry since
i first published that book
or rather in the industry has
professionalized a lot so people rather
than working at night it's a lot more
you know what we want work-life balance
we are professionals we
especially the corporate programmers
they have a lot more of a professional
attitude towards all this it's like i
come in at 9am or whatever works for me
and i finish when i finish because i
have a life outside of this i have kids
take care of i have family you know i
don't want to spend my entire life
programming whereas the younger folks or
the people who have like indie hackers
or people who have side hustles there's
a lot of working at night or working on
the weekends just because you like it
and honestly
if you look at open source i think a lot
of that does still happen at night
especially for
people who aren't doing it full-time
it's like you either wake up early and
you get
two or three hours of coding on your
favorite open source project or pet idea
before you start with the meetings and
the boring stuff and like oh yes i
managed to write five lines of code at
work today it's like
i just spent two hours in flow working
on some really interesting problem that
really pulled me in and i almost forgot
to go to work
very different modes right agreed before
we conclude the catch-all question
was there anything i missed that you
would like to mention
i think i'd like to mention that a lot
of the senior mindset stuff that we've
been talking about is on
seniormindset.com and it became an ebook
as well that people are really enjoying
and it's kind of a combination between
how to be a true senior engineer how to
think that stuff and also different
career paths and approaches to
how to leverage
the actual senior engineering stuff to
having a better life outside of
engineering because you know it turns
out that we don't have to think about
code and technical stuff all the time
there's a lot of other things out there
i'll make sure i link to that in the
show notes people can follow you on
twitter but how else can people get in
touch
yeah so i'm at swizzits on twitter i
have a blog on swizzles.com that has a
newsletter and i try to be really good
with replying to everyone
who writes me an email or replies to one
of my things i don't always get to it on
right away but i try to get there
eventually
swiss thank you for coming on this show
it's been a real pleasure this is
bridget shamanit for software
engineering radio thank you for
listening yeah thank you for having me
this was great
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at
se-radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for
[Music]